[Music]
Hey,
hey, hey, hey.
[Music]
Well, good morning everyone and welcome
to the Fiber Broadband Association's
Fire for Breakfast. We're now in our
21st episode of 2025. Before we kick
off, I'd like to thank Westco, the
platinum sponsor fire for breakfast.
Well, in Washington this morning, there
are two key hearings related to fiber
broadband which will be take place in
Congress. The House Appropriations
Committee will hold an oversight hearing
of the FCC with Chairman Carr as their
witness. Also in the House, the
Subcommittee on Commerce, Manufacturing,
and Trade will hold the educational
hearing on AI. In preparation, the Fiber
Broadband Association has shared our AI
and fiber report with the subcommittee.
And recently, Senate leaders continued
to urge NTI to move quickly as possible
on releasing the bead funding. US
Senator Shelley Moore Capido of West
Virginia recently sent a letter to US
Secretary of Commerce Howard Lutnik
asking for an expedited review and
updated guidance for the beat program
urging that West Virginia not have to
wait on significant or have significant
revisions to its application.
Additionally, a letter from nine Senate
Democrats led by Senator Jackie Rosen of
Nevada was sent on Friday to President
Trump with a similar request. You know,
further related to bead, state broadband
officers were notified that the digital
equity act fund would be ended
immediately. Additionally, top tech
leaders including Open AI's Sam Alman
appeared before the Senate Commerce
Committee. Lawmakers focus on topics
such as advancing US global
competitiveness and AI, light touch
regulations, permitting challenges, and
workforce issues. Most notably, Senator
Morgan of Kansas noted that rural areas
lack sufficient broadband and AI
requires broadband. So, we're now just
weeks, well, not even weeks, a week and
a half away from Fiberconnect 2025 in
Nashville, which kicks off on June 1st.
and we continue to set uh new attendance
records every year for the past five
years and 2025 will be no exception.
That's going to be between five and
6,000 of our closest friends. So, if you
haven't registered, please go to
fiberblad.org under events and register
today. Uh you're not going to want to
miss uh fiberconnect 2025. So, after the
the big event in Nashville, we'll
continue to work our way around North
America. So far, regional workshops in
San Antonio and Philly have been sold
out, and our next regional workshop will
be in Anchorage, Alaska on July 17th.
After Anchorage, we'll be in Toronto in
August, Spokane in September, Scottsdale
in October, Kansas City in November, and
Palm Springs will be our premier member
meeting December 8th and 9th. You know,
last week I showed this fiber
availability map. David, can you put
that map
up? And you know, we'll this today we'll
be discussing Oklahoma. From a study,
Oklahoma had 3.2% fiber in 2013, which
increased to 11.6% fiber by 2016, and
has greatly improved to
64.2% by
2024. Oklahoma plans to get to 95% fiber
by 2028. As of June 2024, Oklahoma had
250,000 unserved and underserved
locations, which is about 15% of the
families of the state. So today on Fire
for Breakfast, our guest is Mike
Sanders, the executive director of the
Oklahoma Office to discuss Fiber
Forward, Oklahoma's bold path to
statewide connectivity. But before I
formulate today's guest, I'd like to
introduce David Norris from team to walk
us through house some housekeeping
items.
Thank you very much, Gary, and thank you
to everyone who's joined us today. We
appreciate it. Uh before I go over a few
logistics, we'd like to just once again
thank our platinum sponsor, Fiber for
Breakfast West Co. Now, please keep in
mind as a participant, you are in
listenon mode today. To ask a question,
please type it into the question box,
which is located in the lower left hand
side of your screen, and we will have a
Q&A session with our panelists at the
end of today's presentation. This
presentation is also being recorded and
will be available on FDA's website
within 24 to 48 hours and you can find
that recording in the events tab under
the fiber for breakfast dropdown option.
Finally, at the conclusion of the
presentation today, you'll be prompted
to complete a brief feedback survey.
Please take a moment to do so. We
appreciate your input. With that, I will
hand things back over to Gary to get us
started. Gary, thanks David and good
morning. I'm Gary Bolton, the president
and CEO of the Fiber Broadband
Association. Last week on Fiber
Breakfast, our guest was Christina
Wilston, the CEO of Old Harbor Native
Corporation, who discussed Project
Noneet, connecting tribal communities
and culture across Kodiak Island.
Christina outlined um the challenging
environment for broadband in Alaska. And
I'm excited to say the Fiber Broadband
Association will be uh in Alaska on July
17th for our regional fiber connect
workshop. So, we're looking forward to
seeing firsthand what's going on in
Alaska.
U today on Fire for Breakfast, our guest
is Mike Sanders, the executive director
of the Oklahoma Broadband Office to
discuss Fiber Forward, Oklahoma's bold
path to statewide connectivity. Mike was
appointed as executive director of the
Oklahoma Broadband Office in March 2023
and under his leadership, the office has
expanded his professional team and is
focused on achieving efficient
operations. Prior to taking this role,
he founded and operated his own
business, Sanders Strategy and
Consulting Group. He also had an
impactful political career serving six
terms in the Oklahoma House of
Representatives starting in 2008. During
his tenure in the House, he uh led his
leadership and positions included chair
of the House Utilities Committee and
Appropriations and Budget Subcommittee
on Transportation. He also served as the
House Majority Leader. Prior to his
legislative services, uh Sanders served
as the director of interns in the White
House for President George W. Bush Bush
and he played a key role in revitalizing
the house white house intern programs
received the distinguished honor service
award for his dedication of or dedicated
service on September 11th 2001. Sanders
continued his public service in the Bush
administration with senior management
roles at United States Department of
Agriculture. He worked as a senior
adviser to the chief of the USDA Natural
Resource Conservation Service and as a
deputy chief of staff in the uh USDA
Rural Development. Sanders earned his
undergraduate degree in history and
pre-law from Oklahoma Christian
University and pursued further studies
at Georgetown where he worked his
master's degree in government. Born and
raised in King Fischer, Sanders resides
there with his wife Nelly and his sons
Davis and Walker. So welcome Mike and
for audience please type in your
questions as you go and work those into
the
discussion. Mike just a real pleasure to
have you here. So Mike um you know given
your extensive um experience both at the
state national level I didn't know that
it's going to be so critical for your
role as a state broadband director but
can you talk a little bit about um you
know how you've been able to lean on
your past experience and even working at
USDA and so forth? Absolutely. And Gary,
thank you for having me this morning.
I'm looking forward to uh to our chat
today. You know, I I never thought in a
million years that I would have the
honor and and responsibility and role
that I currently have, but I will tell
you that it has come um it has come uh
as as as the experience in my past. It's
been very valuable to use. I will say
that. Uh I've been very blessed in in in
my career. Uh, and again, ultimately,
you know, I've I still currently live in
rural Oklahoma. I I I uh represented uh
six wonderful rural western Oklahoma uh
counties. Uh so I live it, breathe it,
and and eat it every day. But I will
tell you uh working in Washington uh
gave me vast experience to to to learn
firsthand the connectivity issues that
we have in our state and quite frankly
the country because we've been talking
about lack thereof connectivity for
decades. This is not
a an entity or or a uh an issue that
that has just come to light over the
last five years. Uh but I will also
share that that experience really helped
me navigate uh through the state
legislature uh dealing with uh utilities
when I was chair of that committee uh
certain issues that were uh very
important to internet service providers.
So, it has helped me, it has helped my
team uh navigating some of these
pitfalls and these uh potholes, you
could say, uh as we navigate this very
dicey uh dicey move uh in in in the
world of broadband.
Well, listen, um you know, Oklahoma has
a very aggressive plan to get to 95%
fiber. Um you know, you're leveraging a
number of um opportunities. uh you know
the American Rescue Plan, the capital
projects fund and then hopefully we'll
see some bead money at some point is you
know how what do you have to do to get
to 95%. And that's a short period of
time. You know it's halfway through 2025
to be able to get there by 2028.
Absolutely. And and and so let let me
kind of start backwards and then we'll
move forward. Um, our
legislature wanted our office here at
the Oklahoma Broadband Office to make
sure that we get to 95% connectivity
when this program or when this office
goes away uh in three years. Um, we'll
be north of that, but it's going to take
all the other federal programs and the
flexibility for our state to to achieve
that. And and I can get into that a
little bit later in the conversation.
uh but we have taken a bold very
aggressive step or steps uh to make sure
that we do that and I think flexibility
has a lot to do with that because when
you look when you look at the the amount
of money that we have to spend we we
will get close to that 95% but I think
when you look at the other monies that
are involved in that space in the
broadband space with USDA uh reconnect
monies the the FCC monies with enhanced
AAM, the NIA tribal monies. Uh sometimes
people forget, you know, Oklahoma has 39
nationally recognized tribal nations. Um
so we have that component. Um and then
of course, you know, the the past
history of of Ardoff and and other
programs. Uh we will get to that 95. In
fact, like I said, we will get over
that, but it's going to take every one
of us, all these programs working hand
inand to make sure that we do that. Um,
but again, at the end of the day, our
goal is to take care of those unserved
and underserved Oklahomaans. We believe
our program is a step in the absolute
right direction. Uh, but we will need
others to to to join. And it's amazing
what happens when we can build a
coalition, which we've done, uh, to make
sure that we reach that goal and
actually exceed that goal. As long as
I'm sitting in this chair, Gary, I plan
to exceed that goal.
So given your, you know, past experience
in the White House and then as a state
legislator, um, what do we need to do to
help Washington understand that the
state broadband directors intimately
know your budget, every location, your
topology, and the families you're trying
to serve. I mean, it I can't imagine
anybody being in a better position to
make the right choices.
you you are 10,000% right and it all
starts with open communication. Um I I
will tell you what Oklahoma has done. Uh
we have communicated clearly and
effectively with our federal delegation.
Number one, uh we communicate uh on a
very regular basis. um either through
teams meetings or if I have to make a
trip to Washington, I will do that.
Letting them know what our budget is,
letting them know that we're limited.
Here are our
successes. Here are things that that we
would love to see uh from the new
administration. Uh and every new
administration when you when you come
into a situation like this should have
an opportunity to to review all policies
from a previous administration. But
we've been waiting for bead and this
broadband expansion for a long long time
and and I would hate to see more uh
delays. U but back to what we were
saying a second ago. I think open
communication uh is is is paramount.
We've also set up meetings with our uh
with the uh new administration uh some
of the folks at NIA uh some of the folks
at commerce. Obviously NIA is underneath
commerce. Um but again it's about
relationships. Everything that we do,
Gary, you know this better than anybody.
You know, past experiences, past lives,
those type of relationships help us get
inside and get inside the door, get
inside the office to have those
conversations. And and and here's the
deal. We we have the um expert uh e
expertise, if you will. Uh but we're
going to need folks like you and and and
other folks in this broadband space to
make sure that we can articulate
correctly. Uh but it all boils down to
communication and then ultimately
ultimately our goal in that
communication is to make sure that the
new administration and our federal
delegation understand that with our
monies that we have, we know the state
better than anybody. Most people don't
realize that Oklahoma has 10 different
types of terrain uh in in in our 77
counties plus our tribal nations that
that we work with hand in hand. Um so
again, education, communication
um are are are key, but flexibility is
what we're wanting the outgrowth of
those meetings that we have and will
have. We want to make sure that they
know, my team and I know what's best.
Um, and again, don't mind the parameters
being set. I think there needs to be
parameters being set. Absolutely. Um,
but again, giving us the flexibility to
to apply our expertise is is is what's
going to get us north of 95% and and
closer to that 100% connectivity. Uh,
which is the whole premise and and and
and the DNA or inside the DNA of of be.
So again, we're looking forward to
having those continued conversations u
because it's critical. I am beholden to
the taxpayer. I'm also beholden to the
folks here in rural Oklahoma that have
been waiting decades to have the
opportunity to be connected. I think we
owe it to them. Uh and as long as I'm
sitting in this chair, that is my goal
to achieve that. So, let's just kind of
drill down and be Where are you? You
guys are just wrapping up your
application window this week. We It'll
be a week from today. Uh 11:59 p.m. on
Memorial Day. Uh we will conclude that
we've had our application process open
for nearly a month. Uh what I really
really like is how we did
things playing a role in in this overall
fix. Um so before we were able to submit
our final proposal uh draft one if you
will, we were able to include uh
alternative types. uh we wrote that into
our our plan. Um so that's something
that I that I saw my team saw and I
think that has given us the flexibility
that once plans are reviewed and the
overall beach strategy is reviewed I
think we fit nicely uh into that. But I
will say that Oklahoma um you know our
preference again has has has always been
um has always been fiber. You know, I'm
not I'm not out to use or use other
technologies against other technologies
because I ultimately believe it's going
to take every one of us. It's going to
take the fixed wireless and the
unlicensed fixed wireless. And I think
there is a a role for for LEO uh to to
be at the table. Our preference, of
course, is fiber, but again, you are
only limited to so much money. So I
think if all of us can can get in a room
and and continue to build a coalition
and coalition and understand that
unserved and unserved Oklahomaans are
are our customers, that's what we have
to do and we have to make sure that we
do it on time. uh which is another uh
critical issue that I'm I'm hopeful that
the dates can be moved back to allow
companies the opportunity to build and
go through some of this permitting
process which I hope uh some of that
gets gets fixed in the pause for bead u
but again there's a lot of moving parts
but we're ultimately wanting to to make
sure that Oklahomaans can decide what's
best for Oklahoma uh not you know
perhaps bureaucrats in in Washington DC
So, I mean, we have I know we haven't
seen guidance yet from whatever
revisions NTI might may or may not want
to put in, but um it it's it appears
that non-employment funds is some
concerns. Um although, you know, middle
mile and workforce development are both
highly supported by the new
administration and those are eligible
expenses. Have you guys kind of shifted
how you think about non-employment? if
you have any funds available. We we have
and and I'm glad you brought up
Middlemont because through our ARPA
state and local fiscal recovery fund
monies uh that were announced over a
year ago, uh we had some some uh
companies who decided not to go forward.
So, we were able to reallocate that
money and just last week, this is
perfect timing, Gary, just last week,
uh, we were able to announce over $53
million in middle mile projects that
went to five internet service companies
in 19 different locations. Um, so we
were really really um, uh, proud and and
honored that we were able to do that
because I don't think there's anyone in
the industry that that would be opposed
to that because that ultimately leads to
better last mile uh, connectivity and
and and enforces and and and builds up
uh, you know, our last mile uh,
connections. Uh so we've been very
thoughtful, very um uh pro-thinking,
pro-forward thinking on on that and I
know there's a lot of uh talk and uh
about using non-employment monies. We've
already started that and I think the
administration will be very happy with
the results that we uh here in Oklahoma
have have carried on and carried
through.
So obviously Oklahoma's pretty famous
for its weather.
Yeah. So I think they have a few movies
about that, but it's um are so is it the
your cost of employment higher than
other states or I mean what what's what
do you have to take uh you do you try to
bury your facilities or how are you
prioritizing to make sure you have
strong resiliency? Well, I think a lot
of that has to do with so far of of the
programs that we've been very honored
and blessed to to to get out the door.
Obviously, our ARPA monies. Um, and I
got to give a lot of credit to our
legislature here in Oklahoma because
they had the foresight to to use ARPA
monies, both the capital projects fund
as well as the state and local fiscal
recovery funds and dedicate uh over $500
million of that into broadband
infrastructure last mile projects. Um,
of those projects, 80% are fiber. 80%
are fiber. The other 20% uh is fixed
wireless. We know with the tornadoes, we
know with the wind uh putting that uh
infrastructure conduit into the ground
is is by far the best. Yes, it is
expensive. However, you get sometimes
what you pay for. And if you are able to
put that infrastructure into the ground,
um that that protects you from, you
know, 70 mph wind on, you know, just a
regular old day here in Oklahoma or
tornadoes or some of the massive massive
uh forest fires that that we have had
here in the state. It protects uh from
the the
towers or perhaps if you have aerial
fiber because a lot of telephone poles
uh on those pole attachments are wood
and and and those burn pretty easily
when you have uh 60 foot 70 foot flames
uh from a wildfire. So, you know, our
emphasis has been and our companies here
in Oklahoma know that um and and they
have predominantly have put that in the
ground. Uh and it lasts longer and
that's and that's another uh another
reason why I think when you're looking
at building this out and the cost of it
has been um tornadoes, fire, and ice, I
almost forgot about, you know, the ice
storms that we've had here in Oklahoma.
You put all that in the ground, you
avoid all that. And again, when you
think about a public safety standpoint,
from a communication standpoint, those
are areas of of critical concern and and
our team has put that and put that
thought into wanting to make sure that
our fiber is is is buried uh as opposed
to not being buried.
So, I mean, obviously, the other thing
that's different about Oklahoma than
other states is you the number of
tribes. Can you talk a little bit about
the coordination and then how people are
um the you know that are going to be
bidding on bead awards how they're
leveraging because that you can
eliminate the match right if you put
tribal um locations in here. Correct.
Yes. And that's what we've done that's
what we've done here in Oklahoma. Um,
and you know, one of the great things,
Gary, is that, you know, um, Oklahoma,
uh, if you if you look at the the the
breakout of of our state, our state's
name, it's it it's land of the red man.
And, you know, we're very proud of our
our Native American heritage and the 39
tribes that call Oklahoma home. And one
of the first things that we did here uh
was to hire a coordinator that
coordinates all of the different
meetings that go into our final
proposal, meeting with our tribal
nations and and and letting them uh you
know know of our programs moving
forward. And and I can tell you that we
know that there's going to be some great
applications. Twothirds of Oklahoma land
uh are tribal lands. Um and and so
again, when you look at that and look at
the makeup of our of our state, uh we
are
absolutely uh wanting to make sure that
we have a great partnership and and and
we do have a great partnership with all
of our tribes and gone across the state
meeting with those um wonderful
wonderful folks. Um you know, and and
you know, one of the things that I think
is is is
critical, they have to be part of this
discussion.
they and they have been we we've had
meetings throughout the state. We we've
had seminars, webinars, you name it. Um
it is interesting
because this is something that a lot of
states, you know, they don't have a lot
of tribal partners. uh we have and we
have opened up that door and our
coordinator has done a fabulous job in
and in in answering questions uh holding
their hands because this is something
entirely brand new for not only our
tribal nations but for everybody, right?
So we we've been very very um uh pro
forward thinking on on making sure that
our tribal partners have a seat uh at
our table. uh because after all, the
only way that we're going to be able to
get uh and pass or surpass our 95%
uh connectivity here in the state of
Oklahoma is is to make sure that they're
involved. They will be. Past experiences
has has proven that. When we announced
our middle mile uh projects last week,
uh we had uh had several of our uh
grants go to a uh a tribal nation. So,
we're excited. We we know that it's
going to take a lot of work. It's going
to take a lot of time. Uh but anything
worthwhile in life, I have learned in
past experiences is is is putting the
the time in and working with our tribal
partners.
So, I mean, I know it's kind of an
awkward um time right now for broadband
directors when there's supposed to be
some kind of revision to the plans and
you're having to operate from the plans,
you know, um how do you anticipate
Um, is it just going to be lucky that
the timing you have that um, you should
know revisions before you're ready to
submit your final proposal or do you I
mean what how do you can you handicap
how things are going to play out for
Oklahoma? Well, I tell you what, Gary,
if if I knew if I knew that answer, you
and I would be in Vegas tonight. Um, but
I will say this and and kidding aside,
you know, I I think um just looking at
it from a political
um
prism, um we've been lucky here in
Oklahoma
that with our previous monies um here
with our
ARPA, state and local fiscal recovery
fund, our middle mile project, and our
capital projects funds, we've been able
to get those out the door. Construction
on all of those projects excluding
middle mile is at 73% 73% of those
projects are underway. The 180
um workforce we've been able to get
folks uh keep those folks uh or will be
able to keep those folks here once be
released. Um, a lot of this is hedging
bets, I guess, is the best way to do
that, but also understanding
understanding
uh what the political tea leaves are
saying. Um, you know, we haven't been so
staunch, stubborn that it's going to be
one way or the other because at the end
of the day, uh, we will get our marching
orders and we will march. uh but
hopefully the way that we have written
our proposal uh will will uh will be
great for the administration, the new
administration. I think they will see
that we have and and have included
everybody to be at the table. Um it is
frustrating I know uh for folks that
have been waiting for a long time to get
highspeed internet as we've gone around
the state the last two years telling
folks that it's going to be here um or
it's coming. Uh I hope that the 90day
uh pause only stays 90 days because for
Oklahoma that puts us to the end of
October. Uh we want to get shovels in
the ground now. We want to put our
workforce Oklahoma workforce behind
those particular uh projects. We want to
keep those jobs here. We want to make
sure that we uh not only are are ahead
of the ahead of the curve, but but also
want to make sure if the timelines don't
change that we meet everything on time
and on budget. So, you know, reading the
tea leaves, having open communication
with with the with the new uh
administration, I think is is is key.
Uh, you know, I have to say that they've
they they've been very very good to work
with uh from from our standpoint. Um,
and you know, we just got to continue to
keep moving uh moving the the can down
the road because we we don't have time.
Time is is is of the essence and time is
not on our side, especially if they
don't move move that scale back. So, you
know, we've got to continue to work and
move forward. Um, some states have
paused. Uh, some states have been told
to pause. Um, you know, we've been
moving ahead. I I think that's what we
have to do. Uh, because at the end of
the day, we're beholden to the taxpayers
of this state and this country. Well,
Mike, um, thank you for everything, your
service, and everything you do for the
state of Oklahoma. Um, excited for you
guys. Looking for you to get to hit your
go surpass your 95% target. I know
you'll be able to do that and look
forward to seeing you in Nashville here
in a week or so. I want to thank
everybody for joining us today and look
forward to getting back together next
Wednesday. We're going to be with Juliet
Frink Yates, the broadband
infrastructure and digital inclusion
manager for the city of Philadelphia.
It's going to discuss the Phil Connect
Ed program and the city's digital
navigator network. So, we see you guys
uh well, I guess that's in two weeks.
We'll see you guys in two weeks. Thanks.